Kiprono Elijah Koech | Résumé

Nairobi, Kenya

§ + (254) 704 50 0007
■ kiprono@aims.ac.za
■ 'n kipronokoech.github.io/

in: https://www.linkedin.com/in/kipronokoech

Summary

An experienced, highly analytical and results-oriented data scientist and statistician focus on being a grounded researcher in machine learning and deep learning.

Graduate of Stellenbosch University and Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology with a Masters Degree in Mathematical Sciences and Bachelors Degree in Statistics, respectively. Recently finish a program towards Masters Degree in Applied Mathematics at Stellenbosch University. Also worked as a Research Fellow at Technische Universität Berlin recently.

Possessing working knowledge in programming languages like Python and R with the application on Data Science fields like Predictive Modeling, Data Analytics, Computer Vision, among other areas.

Key Skills

Areas of Expertise.....

Deep Learning Machine Learning

Computer Vision

Applied Statistics

Data Visualization

Data Mining

Business Intelligence and Analytics

Applied Mathematics

Reproducible Research

Tools and Technologies...

Python

Git Version Control

R (familiar)

LATEX

TensorFlow and Keras

AWS

HTML and CSS

Tableau

Microsoft Office Suite

Docker **SPSS**

Education

Stellenbosch University

Cape Town, South Africa

Certificate(Anticipated): Master's Degree in Applied Mathematics (Data Science)

Anticipated graduation: March 2022

Research area: Deep Learning

Stellenbosch University

Cape Town, South Africa

Certificate: Master's Degree in Mathematical Sciences, Cum Laude

Jan 2019 - Nov 2019

Feb 2020 - Dec 2021

Research area: Machine Learning and Computer Vision

Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology

Nairobi, Kenya

Certificate: Bachelors Degree in Science (Statistics), First Class Honors

Sep 2013 - Nov 2017

Work Experience

Research Fellow, Science of Intelligence

Berlin, Germany

A brief: Worked on a computer vision project at Technische Universität Berlin.

Feb 2021 - Aug 2021

Worked on action recognition problem

Data Science Technical Mentor, Great Learning - Olympus

(Remote) Texas, U.S.A

A brief: A mentorship and tutoring role for data science students.

Nov 2020 - Aug 2021

 Mentored and tutored 6 students per semester taking a course in Data Science and Business Analytics at Olympus, attaining 100% successful completion of the course.

Data Assistant, CDC-University of Maryland

Kisii and Migori, Kenya

A brief: Data entry, management and analysis role involving HIV patients information.

Jan 2018 – Dec 2018

- Managed HIV patients data for over 10,000 clients. This involved entering information on the paper into the IQ care database; analyze the data to locate clients with poor adherence and recommend follow-up; and data quality checks.
- Follow-up reduced the cases of poor adherence to anti-retroviral by over 70% and be able to close cases as required. Rectified an event that almost led to the loss of 2300 data points due to system failure. The by-product of this was setting up a more robust backup pipeline.

Statistician Intern, South Nyanza (SONY) Sugar Company

Migori, Kenya

A brief: An internship working with factory data in a sugar company.

Jun 2017 - Dec 2017

- Analyzed factory data to explain production trends and seasonality phenomena.
- Particularly analyzed downtime data and reported variables that are most significant in impacting the extent of downtime. Upon implementation, there was a 42% drop in downtime in 2018 compared to 2017.

Projects

- 1. Reviews Classification | Skills: Web scraping, Sklearn, machine learning algorithms
 - \circ This project involves scraping over 200k reviews using Scrapy and classifying them as positive or negative using different Sklearn models. Also, dealing with the issue of data imbalance.
 - SVM classifier was the best in this application achieving an F1 score of 89%... the code is in this GitHub repo.
- 2. Fruit Detection | Skills: Python, TensorFlow and Keras, Computer Vision
 - In this project, Mask R-CNN and YOLOv5 are deployed in context from fruit detection on outdoor images (apples and mangoes).
 - The two models achieved on-par state-of-the-art results attaining 93% and 88% F1 score for mango and apple images, respectively... more information in GitHub.
- 3. Crop Disease Classification | Skills: Python, TensorFlow and Keras, Computer Vision
 - This is classification problem applied to Agriculture. This project was presented as a solution to a Zindi Challenge and ranked as top 15% solution...more information in GitHub.

Award and Honors

Golden Key Award, for being among the top 15% academic performers among the 2019 cohort. (2020-2022)

African Institute for Mathematical Sciences(AIMS) Scholarship, for MSc Mathematics at S.U (2019-2010)&(2020-2021)

Award for Excellence, African Institute for Mathematical Sciences(AIMS)

(Jan 2019- Nov 2019)

Vice-Chancellors Academic Award, the best student in Bachelor of Science (Statistics option)

(2014/2015, 2015/2016 and 2016/2017 academic years)

First place, Mathematics contest with 1954 contestants (2012)

Groups and Societies

- Computer Vision and Remote Sensing Group at Technische Universität Berlin, Germany [1] [2]
- Data Science Research Group at African Institute for Mathematical Sciences, South Africa [1]
- Golden Key International Honour Society
- Kenya National Society of Statisticians